Preliminary Guide to the McFadden Family papers, 1921-2002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McFadden Family papers 1921-2002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McFadden family
6.5 linear feet Extent: 4875 Items
William Allen McFadden (1904-1991), Methodist minister from Indiana, graduate of DePauw, Boston University School of Theology, and Union Seminary in New York. He was a lifelong pacifist and social justice worker. His wife was Glenora English McFadden (1910-2001) and her mother was Estella Graves English (1885-1960). The McFaddens had three children: Margaret McFadden (whose papers are also housed in the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture), Edith Collins, and David McFadden. This collection consists of numerous accessions containing correspondence, audiocassettes, diaries, photographs, yearbooks, printed materials, newspaper clippings, and other miscellaneous materials, largely produced by William and Glenora McFadden during their courtship and marriage, 1921-1991. Also included is correspondence from Glenora McFadden's mother, Estella Graves English, and correspondence from Margaret McFadden, the McFaddens' daughter. Please consult the Collection Overview below for more information about the materials in each accession.
RL.00871
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The McFadden Family Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2005 and 2007.
Biographical Note
William Allen McFadden (1904-1991), Methodist minister from Indiana, graduate of DePauw, Boston University School of Theology, and Union Seminary in New York. He was a lifelong pacifist and social justice worker. His wife was Glenora English McFadden (1910-2001) and her mother was Estella Graves English (1885-1960). The McFaddens had three children: Margaret McFadden (whose papers are also housed in the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture), Edith Collins, and David McFadden.
Collection Overview
The accession (2005-0028) (300 items, 0.6 lin. ft.; dated 1936-1994 and undated) consists of sermons, letters, and diaries of William Allen McFadden, 1930-1991; sermons, journals, and letters of Glenora English McFadden, circa 1936-1994; and letters of Estella Graves English, 1959-1986. Includes a genealogy list compiled by Irene English Shoemaker. Also contains ephemera, photographs, and clippings.
The addition (2005-0092) (404 items, 0.6 lin. ft.; dated ca. 1936-2000) contains correspondence to Glenora and Bill McFadden. Also includes photographs, 2 audiotapes, and clippings.
The addition (2007-0048) (760 items, 1.7 lin. ft.; dated 1921-2001) contains sermons, correspondence, and a typescript for History of Israel. Also includes Glenora English's school notebooks; a William McFadden notebook; a yearbook from Bedford High School, 1921; two yearbooks from De Pauw University, 1922 and 1925; and a glass slide.
The 2007 addition (2007-0125) (400 items, 0.8 lin. ft.; dated 1921-1998) contains printed materials, manuscripts, correspondence, sermons, and clippings as well as a yearbook, diary, and commonplace book.
The 2007 addition (2007-0215) (1000 items; 2 lin. ft.; dated 1926-2001) includes correspondence, scrapbooks, audio cassette tapes with recorded sermons, a yearbook, diaries, and photographs from the McFadden family, including letters from Bill to Glenora prior to their marriage. Also included is schoolwork from Margaret McFadden's childhood and high school years, and correspondence from her dating from the 1970s.
The 2009 addition (2009-0207) (2 items; 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1928) includes 2 school notebooks belonging to Glenora English; one consists of her notes from American History and one is a project about United States geography.
The 2013 addition (2013-0188) (375 items; 0.5 lin. ft; dated 1993-2002) consists mainly of family correspondence.
Subject Headings
McFadden Family; Sermons, American -- 20th century; Audiocassettes; Photographs; Diaries
Contents of Collection
- Accession (2005-0028), 1 Box
  Accession (300 items, 0.6 lin. ft.; dated 1936-1994 and undated) contains sermons, letters, and diaries of William Allen McFadden, 1930-1991; sermons, journals, and letters of Glenora English McFadden, circa 1936-1994; and letters of Estella Graves English, 1959-1986. Includes a genealogy list compiled by Irene English Shoemaker. Also contains ephemera, photographs, and clippings. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Journals (Box 1)
  - Diaries (Box 1)
  - Sermons (Box 1)
- Accession (2005-0092), 1 Box (Box 1)
  Addition (404 items, 0.6 lin. ft.; dated ca. 1936-2000) comprises correspondence to Glenora and Bill McFadden. Also includes photographs, 2 audiotapes, and clippings.
  - Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Financial records (Box 2)
  - Photographs, (29 items) (Box 2)
  - Audiocassettes, (2 items) (Box 2)
- Accession (2007-0048), 4 Boxes (Box 2)
  Addition (760 items, 1.7 lin. ft.; dated 1921-2001) contains sermons, correspondence, and a typescript for History of Israel. Also includes Glenora English's school notebooks; a William McFadden notebook; a yearbook from Bedford High School, 1921; two yearbooks from De Pauw University, 1922 and 1925; and a glass slide.
  - Correspondence, 1961-2001 (Box 3)
  - Sermons, 1970s-1980s (Box 3)
  - Our Camping Philosophy for Junior High Camps (Box 3)
  - Typescript of History of Israel (Box 3)
  - Sermons, 1960s-1980s (Box 4)
  - The Mirage: the Official Yearbook of De Pauw University, 1922 (Box 5)
  - The Mirage: the Official Yearbook of De Pauw University, 1925 (Box 5)
  - Glenora McFadden commonplace book (Box 5)
  - William McFadden notebook (Box 5)
  - Glenora Belle English notebook, 1928 (Box 6)
  - Bedford High School Yearbook, 1921 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook (Box 6)
- Accession (2007-0125), 2 Boxes (Box 6)
  The 2007 addition (400 items, 0.8 lin. ft.; dated 1921-1998) contains printed materials, manuscripts, correspondence, sermons, and clippings as well as a yearbook, diary, and commonplace book.
  - Scrapbook (Box 7)
  - Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Sermons (Box 7)
  - Story: Why the Chimes Ring (Box 7)
  - Printed materials (Box 7)
  - Clippings (Box 7)
  - Yearbook (Box 7)
  - William McFadden Diary, 1927 (Box 8)
  - Glenora English commonplace book (Box 8)
- Accession (2007-0215), 4 Boxes (Box 8)
  Addition (1000 items; 2 lin. ft.; dated 1926-2001) includes correspondence, scrapbooks, audio cassette tapes with recorded sermons, a yearbook, diaries, and photographs from the McFadden family, including letters from Bill to Glenora prior to their marriage. Also included is schoolwork from Margaret McFadden's childhood and high school years, and correspondence from her dating from the 1970s.
  - Glenora McFadden estate, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Letters from Bill to Glenora, 1933 (Box 9)
  - Address book (Box 9)
  - Letters and postcards to Glenora and William McFadden, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    Mostly from Margaret from Europe (1971-1974), California and Colorado (1974-1975)
  - Miscellaneous clippings and materials, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Make Mine Democracy school project, Margaret McFadden (Box 9)
  - For MM-Duke (Box 9)
  - Margaret McFadden, high school papers (Box 9)
  - Glenora English diary, 1927-1928 (Box 9)
  - Christmas letters (Box 10)
  - Copies of letters from William McFadden to his parents, Laramie, Monta Vista (Box 10)
  - New England Southern Annual Conference journal/yearbook, 1927 (Box 10)
  - DePauw publication (Box 10)
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous, 1923-1990s (Box 10)
  - William and Glenora McFadden memorial information (Box 10)
  - 34 audiocassette tapes (sermons and talks) (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook (Box 12)
  - Worthington Christian Church (Mr. English and family included, 1930s): rolled panoramic photograph (Box 12)
- Accession (2009-0207), (2 items) (Box 12)
  Addition (2009-0207) (2 items; 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1928) includes 2 school notebooks belonging to Glenora English; one consists of her notes from American History and one is a project about United States geography.
  - American presidents notes, 1928 (Box 12)
  - United States geography project (Box 12)
- Accession (2013-0188), (1 box) (Box 12)
  - Family correspondence and personal papers dated from 1973-2002. (Box 13)